[Music]
foreign
the first surgical attempt at Body
Sculpting was in 1921 with a dancer
wanting to improve the shape of her
ankles the surgeon apparently scraped
away too much tissue and tied the
stitches too tight resulting in necrosis
amputation and the first recorded
malpractice suit in the history of
plastic surgery
today's liposuction is much safer only
killing about one in five thousand
patients mostly from unknown causes
throwing a clot off into your lung or
perforations of your internal organs
liposuction currently rains as the most
popular cosmetic surgery in the world
and its effects are indeed only cosmetic
I started publishing the New England
Journal of Medicine assessed obese women
before and after having about 20 pounds
of fat sucked out of their bodies
resulting in nearly a 20 drop in their
total body fat normally lose even just
five to ten percent of your body weight
and fat and you get significant
improvements in blood pressure blood
sugars inflammation cholesterol and
triglycerides but liposuction sucks none
of those benefits materialized even
after the massive liposuction this
suggests subcutaneous fat the fat under
our skin is not the problem the
metabolic insults of obesity arise from
the visceral fat the fat surrounding or
even infiltrating our internal organs
like the fat marbling our muscles and
liver the way you lose that fat the
dangerous fat is to take in fewer
calories than you burn
anyone who's seen The Biggest Loser
shows knows with enough calorie
restriction in exercise hundreds of
pounds can be lost similarly there are
cases in the medical literature of what
some refer to as super obesity in which
individuals lost up to 374 pounds
largely on their own without
professional help and kept it off for
years the guy lost about 20 pounds a
month cycling two hours a day and
reducing intake to 800 calories a day
which is down around what some prisoners
were getting at concentration camps in
World War II
perhaps America's most celebrated TV
weight loss was when Oprah pulled out a
wagon full of fat representing the 67
pounds she lost on a very low calorie
diet how many calories did she have to
cut to achieve that within four months
consult leading nutrition textbooks or
refer to trusted authorities like the
Mayo Clinic and you'll learn the simple
weight loss rule one pound of fat is
equal to 3 500 calories
quoting from the Journal of the American
Medical Association a total of 3 500
calories equals one pound of body weight
this means if you decrease your intake
by 500 calories daily you will lose one
pound per week 500 calories per day
times seven days equals 3 500 calories
so one pound of body fat the simple
weight loss rule that's simply not true
the 3 500 calorie rule can be traced
back to a paper in 1958 that just noted
that since fatty tissue on the human
body is 87 fat a pound of body fat would
have about 395 grams of pure fat
multiply that by nine calories per gram
of fat gives you that 3 500 calories per
pound approximation the Fatal flaw that
leads to dramatically exaggerated weight
loss predictions is that the 3 500 rule
fails to take into account the fact that
changes in the calories inside of the
energy balance equation automatically
lead to changes in calories out for
example the slowing of metabolic rate
that accompanies weight loss known as
metabolic adaptation that's one of the
reasons weight loss plateaus for example
imagine a 30 year old sedentary woman of
average height who weighs 150 pounds
according to the 3 500 calorie rule if
she cuts 500 calories out of her daily
diet she'd lose a pound a week or 52
pounds a year in three years then she
would banish she'd go from 150 pounds to
negative six obviously that doesn't
happen What would happen is that in the
first year instead of losing 52 pounds
she'd likely lose only 32 pounds and
then after a total of three years
stabilized at about a hundred pounds
this is because it takes fewer calories
to exist as a thin person
part of it is simple mechanics in the
same way a Hummer requires more fuel
than a compact car
think how much more effort it would take
to just get out of a chair walk across
the room or climb a few stairs carrying
a 50 pound backpack that's no lighter
than carrying 50 pounds in the front
even when you're lying at rest sound to
sleep they're simply less of your body
to maintain as we lose weight every
pound of fat tissue lost May mean one
less mile of blood vessels your body has
to pump blood through every minute so
the basic upkeep and movement of thinner
bodies takes fewer calories so as you
lose weight by eating less you end up
needing less
that's what the 3500 calorie rule
doesn't take into account or imagine it
the other way 200 pound man starts
eating 500 more calories a day that's
like a large soda or two Donuts
according to the 3 500 calories rule in
10 years he'd weigh more than 700 pounds
that doesn't happen because the heavier
he is the more calories he burns just
existing if you're 100 pounds overweight
that's like the skinny person inside you
trying to walk around balancing 13
gallons of oil at all times or or
lugging around a sack containing 400
sticks of butter wherever you go
it takes about two Donuts worth of extra
energy just to live at 250 pounds and so
that's where he'd Plateau out if he kept
it up so weight gain or weight loss
given a certain calorie excess or
deficit is a curve that flattens out
over time rather than a straight line up
or down
nevertheless the 3 500 calorie rule
continues to crop up even in obesity
journals Public Health researchers used
it to calculate how many pounds children
might lose every year if for example
fast food kids meals swapped in apple
slices instead of french fries they
figured two meals a week could add up to
about four pounds a year
the actual difference National
Restaurant Association funded
researchers were no doubt delighted to
point out would probably add less than
half a pound 10 times less than the 3
500 calorie rule would predict the
original article was subsequently
retracted
so